[MUSIC PLAYING]
[SILENCE]
If you have perfect knowledge of every single particle in the universe, can
you use the laws of physics tore wind all the wayback to the Big
Bang? Is the entire history of the universe perfectly knowable
[MUSIC PLAYING]
?
or has information somehow been lost along the way?
[MUSIC PLAYING]
The laws of physics are equations of motion. They
are mathematical rules that dictate how systems evolve intime. Newton's
equations for classical mechanics, Maxwell's
equations for electromagnetism, and
the Sch rod inger equation for quantum mechanics. These
laws can be used to predict how the universe will evolve into the future. They
are deterministic. Perfect
knowledge of a system in the present, perfectly
predicts how the system will change in the next instant, and
the instant after that, add
infinitum. But determinism in the forward time direction does not guarantee
that the same laws can perfectly predict the past. And
yet this sort of deterministic symmetry, time
reversal symmetry, is
essential for information itself tobe conserved.
[SILENCE]
Today, we learn why conservation of information is such a
fundamental requirement of quantum mechanics. In
a future episode, we'll
see how this law might be broken by black holes. An
important tool for making predictions with the laws of physics are the conservation laws
that we derive from them. As
we discussed recently, we
can use Notice Theorem to discover quantities that are conserved in a system by
looking at the symmetries of the equations of motion.
For example, if the equations stay the same from one point intime to the next, then
energy is conserved.
Notice theorem applies to smooth, continuous
symmetries where we can transform the chosen coordinate, however
much we like without changing the system.
but there are also symmetries under discrete transformations. They're
more like on / off switches. For
example, we could reverse all electric charges or we could flip the x- axis
by looking in a mirror or we could make time run backwards.
Symmetry in that last one, time
reversal symmetry, isn't
covered by notice theorem, but
it's still tied toa conservation law, the
conservation of information. We
say that a system is time reversal symmetric if its equations of motion allow
us to perfectly predict the starting point simply by knowing the state of
the system at any later time. If
they allow us tore wind the clock and figure out a single unique
history,
The entire universe would betime reversal symmetric if knowing the exact
state of every particle in the universe atone point intime allowed us to calculate
its exact past history at all times. That
would mean that the exact configuration of the universe at any point intime defines
the exact configuration at any other point.
For one thing, this
time reversal symmetry means complete information about the configuration at all prior times
still exists, and always will, even
if we can't practically accessit.
That's what I mean about conservation of information.
A related idea is causal determinism, the
idea that perfectly knowing the current state perfectly predicts all future states. But
this sort of future determinism doesn't have tobe time reversal symmetric. It's
possible for the future tobe perfectly predictable by the laws of physics while the pastis not.
For example, what if many different configurations of particles in the present could
converge ona single configuration of particles in the future?
If a multitude of states can all evolve into the same state, then
knowing the latter state isn't enough for us to figure out what past states led toit.
For example, imagine
you have two states, A
and B, and the laws of motion say that A becomes Cand B
becomes D. If we look at the later state and C states C
, we know A came first, but
if we see stateD, we
know B came first. But
what if both A and B lead to state C?
[SILENCE]
that future direction is deterministic. But
now, if we look at the final state, we
see state c, but we don't know which of aor bled toit.
The
information about those past states would be lost.
Okay, so
it should be simple enough to erase information, right
? We just set things up so our laws of motion force two possible initial
states into the same exact final state. Then
we wouldn't know what the original state was, and
information would be destroyed.
Actually, quantum
mechanics forbids this. It
ensures conservation of information and time reversal symmetry because of an even more fundamental
rule. The conservation of probability.
[SILENCE]
To get at this, let's
think about the basic equation of motion of quantum mechanics. That's
the Sch rod inger equation. The
time- dependent Sch rod inger equation describes the time evolution of this
thing called the wave function. The
wave function of a system fully describes all of its properties, and
in quantum mechanics, that
means the probability distribution of all of its properties, which
you can get by taking the square of the wave function.
[SILENCE]
For example, the wave function of a particle encapsulates the probability
that will be found in this or that location if we were to try to measure
its position. The Schr รถ dinger equation perfectly predicts both
the past and future evolution of a given wave function in any given environment
, or in quantum speak, in
any given potential.
In that sense, it's
deterministic and time reversal symmetric, and
so conserves information.
in principle, a given wave function in a given potential could mean
the wave function of an electron moving in an atom's electric field, or
it could mean the wave function of the entire universe in its own impossibly
complex and changing potential.
[SILENCE]
So, the Sch rod inger equation guarantees time reversibility and so the conservation
of information, as
do the more advanced formulations of quantum mechanics like the Dir ac equation and quantum
field theories.
that guarantee arises from areally fundamental foundational quality of these theories
. It comes from what we call unit arity. Remember
that the wave function encapsulates the distribution of probabilities fora given property. By
definition, those
probabilities should add up to one. That
just means there's a 100 % probability that any given property will have some possible value
, even if that value is zero.
In the case of particle position, probability
of adding to one just means that the particle is definitely somewhere.
And as time goes on, a
particle's properties will continue to have possible values. The
probability should continue to sum to 1.
[SILENCE]
If this is true, and
it must be, we say that the time evolution of the wave function is unitary
. And this unit arity is a foundational assumption in all formulations
of quantum mechanics and quantum field theories.
Uniter ity is anon- negotiable statement about how probability works, but
the condition also ensures time reversal symmetry and conservation of information.
It's not straightforward to explain without getting into some hairy math, but
the upshot is that quantum states must remain independent of each other
in order to preserve probability. Two
independent quantum states can't evolve into the exact same quantum
state. If they did then the probabilities for the initial states, or
for the final state can't both sum to one.
Back to our first example, quantum
states A and B can't both become quantum states C. The
sum of the probabilities prior to the merger would not equal the sum of the probabilities
after the merger and unit arity would be broken. The
only type of evolution that preserves probability and unit arity is the evolution
that also preserves the number of quantum states. And
the preservation of quantum states means preservation of information because you
can trace a quantum state indefinitely forwards and backwards intime
. But all of this talk of quantum mechanics being deterministic seems abit at
odds with the idea of quantum randomness and the uncertainty principle. After
all, doesn't the act of measurement pick a single value of some quantity from
the range of possible values? That
value seems tobe chosen randomly based on the probability distribution
encoded in the wave function. And
the precision of the knowability of that value is defined by the uncertainty
principle. It sure seems like information can be lost.
but that's not really what we mean by quantum information. Quantum
information refers to the full information content of the wave function
, not just what we measure. And
in principle, make
enough measurements and you can extract all of the information from awave function.
It's
worth mentioning that the collapse of the wave function in the Copenhagen interpretation
of quantum mechanics actually does mess with conservation of information
. According to that interpretation, the
active measurement actually alters the entire wave function, causing
it to shrink down to the narrow range of possible values implied by the
result of the measurement.
but that measured wave function can't then be tracked backwards to recover the passed wave function
. Sothis interpretation is neither deterministic nor time reversal symmetric
.
Other interpretations of quantum mechanics, for
example, Everett's
many worlds or the de Bro gl ie- B ohm pilot wave theory, preserve
this time reversibility. In
the case of many worlds, the
entire wave function continues to exist even after measurement.
That measurement itself is just athing that happens inone part of the possibility space
, no information is really lost. And
in the case of pilot wave theory, the
wave function contains hidden information that is carried with the final measured
particle.
[SILENCE]
There is one situation where time reversibility appears tobe broken, regardless
of your favourite interpretation of quantum mechanics. That's
the case of black holes and Hawking radiation. Stephen
Hawking's eponymous radiation appears to destroy quantum information, leading
to the famous black hole information paradox. In
an upcoming episode, we'll
see where the quantum information really can be deleted from the otherwise perfect memory
of spacetime.